A Guide to the Charles Wright Papers ca. 1965-2000
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Charles Wright Papers ca. 1965-2000
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11437-a
This collection contains ca. 1,450 items (housed in 8 Hollinger boxes), chiefly manuscripts and typescripts.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition to the Charles Wright Collection was acquired by the University of Virginia Library from Charles Wright, Charlottesville, Virginia, on January 20, 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Wright (1935- ) is an American poet and University of Virginia English professor.
Scope and Content Information
The writings of Charles Wright include one poetry notebook containing original hand-written poetry by Wright, 1994-1999, page proofs and setting copy for his books Appalachia, Negative Blue Selected Later Poems, and North American Bear, typescripts for individual poems "Lost Language," "On Heaven Considered As What Will Cover Us and Stony Comforter," "Night Rider," "Words for Pliny from the Burning Volcano," "Words for Socrates About Birth & Death," "History & the Sea," "The Poet's Gaze," "Letter from the Stone Age," "Star Magic," and "The Night of 10 August." Also present are translations by Charles Wright of three poems by Italian poet Eugenio Montale.
Most of the correspondence consists of letters, cards, and post cards sent to Charles Wright by fellow poets, fans, and colleagues. These letters have been arranged by the last name of the correspondent, with the more frequent correspondents placed in separate folders. Many of the same correspondents found in the original accession of Charles Wright Papers (#11437) are also represented in this addition to his papers.
Correspondence about awards, conferences, workshops, poetry readings and other professional engagements, poems submitted to or accepted by poetry magazines and anthologies, and requests for Wright to judge poetry contests, write recommendations or evaluate candidates for academic positions; greeting cards; post cards; and invitations are all arranged chronologically by topic.
Also present are some news clippings; printed material; contracts and publication agreements; invitations; writings by other authors about Charles Wright and his work, including a list of interview questions answered by Wright and his comments concerning both Dante and a reading he gave in Wise County, Virginia; and published reviews of his work.
Contents List
- CONTRACTS AND PUBLICATION AGREEMENTS 1967-1999 (Box 1)
- CORRESPONDENCE ca. 1965-2000
  - A 1968-2000 (Box 1)
    including: Tony Abbot, Doug Adams, Leonard Adams, Ai (Florence Anthony), Pam Alexander, George Amabile (1936- ), Jim Amaral (1933- ), Ralph Angel, John [Ashbery]
  - The Academy of American Poets 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Tom Andrews 1987-1999 (Box 1)
  - Awards 1998 (Box 1)
  - B 1967-1999 (Box 1)
    including: Bachi, Russell Banks, Phyllis Barber, Jim Barnes, Bruce Beasley, Ann [Beattie?], Charlotte Beattie, Dan Becker, Calvin Bedient, Erin Belieu, Joan Puma Benner, Kimber Bentley, David Berman, Leslie Berman, [John Berryman?], Chana Bloch, Michael Blumenthal, Don Bogen, Laure-Anne Bosselaar, Vance Bourjaily, Daphne W. Bransten, Elizabeth Brennan, Lucie Brock-Broido, David Brown, Susan Brown, Sharon Bryan, George Butterick
  - Marvin Bell 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Steve Berg 1965-1966, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Robert Bly 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Jim Brasfield 1985-1998 (Box 1)
  - Christopher Buckley 1984-1998 (Box 1)
  - Ca-Cl ca. 1967-1999 (Box 1)
    including: Anne Candelaria, Karen Cangialosi, Catherine Carls, A. Carrera, Fred Chappell, Alan Cheuse, Nicholas Christopher, Amy Clampitt, Killarney Clary
  - Co-Cu ca. 1967-1999 (Box 1)
    including: Michael Collier, Jo Ann Conklin, Harriet Cooper, Matthew Cooper, Alfred Corn, Bonnie Costello, [Fleuri?] Coulette, Steve Coyner, Tony Crunk, Michael Cuddihy
  - D-F 1992-1999 (Box 1)
    including: Alan DeNiro, Carl Dennis, Annie Dillard, John C. Duffey, Reed Finlay, Chris Forhan, Antonella Francini, Phyllis [Franzels?], Alice Fulton
  - David Freed 1985-1999 (Box 2)
  - G 1967-1999 (Box 2)
    including: Jonathan Galassi, George Garrett, Gail Ghai, Dana Gioia, Rebecca Givens, Michelle Glazer, Greg Glazner, Louise Gluck, Jorie Graham, Loren Graham, Katharine Gratwick, Arthur Gregor, Shaun Griffin, Thom Gunn
  - Jim Galvin 1982-1993 (Box 2)
  - Joe Gianelli 1985-1998 (Box 2)
  - Debra Allbery Gildea 1992-2000 (Box 2)
  - Elton Glaser 1975-1999 (Box 2)
  - David Godfrey 1966-1999, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Greeting Cards ca. 1990-1999, n.d. (Box 2)
  - H 1967-1999 (Box 2)
    including: Donald Hall, Sam Hamill, [William] Harmon, Henry Hart, Eleanor Heginbotham, Peter R. Henry, William Heyen, Brenda Hillman, George Hitchcock, Hilary Holladay, Gill Holland, Linda Holtslander, Garrett Hongo, Charles Hood, Linda Howe, Mary Hussman
  - Oakley Hall 1968-1984 (Box 2)
  - Kevin Hart 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - Brian Henry 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - I-J 1987-1999 (Box 3)
    including: Mark Irwin, Rachel Jacoff, Clement Jewitt, Andrew Johnson
  - Invitations to Conferences,Workshops, Poetry Readings, etc. 1975, 1987, 1997-1998 Aug., 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Mark Jarman 1981-1999 (Box 3)
  - Donald Justice 1966-1982, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Donald Justice (Postcards only) 1984-2000 (Box 3)
  - K 1969-1999 (Box 3)
    including: David Kalstone, Karen Kelley, Tim Kendall, Hunter Kennedy, Nancey Kepner, Kerry Shawn Keys, Karl Kirchway, Janet Knepper, Sharon Kubasak
  - L 1975-199 (Box 4)
    including: John Lang, Linda Lappin, Deborah Larsen, Lance Larsen, John Latta, Steve Lautermilch, David Lehman, John Loomis, Lynda Lowe, Tom Lux, Rich Lyons
  - Phil Levine 1967-1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - James Longenbach 1996-1999 (Box 4)
  - M 1966-1999 (Box 4)
    including: Davis McCombs, Cynthia Macdonald, Robert McDowell, Rex McGuinn, Nellie Miller McNeil, Gerard Malanga, Leni Mancuso, Jacqueline Marcus, Paul Mariani, Peter Matthiessen, Bill S. Merwin, Lenny Michaels, Jane Miller, Marta [Mitiovich?], Heather Moore, Robert Morgan, Howard Moss
  - J.D. McClatchy ("Sandy") 1975-2000 (Box 4)
  - Michael McFee 1981-1993 (Box 4)
  - Lynne McMahon 1984-1999 (Box 4)
  - James McMichael 1968-1987 (Box 4)
  - Lynn Martin 1985-1998 (Box 4)
  - Bill Matthews 1974-1997 (Box 4)
  - Robert Mezey 1965-1999 (Box 4)
  - Carol Muske-Dukes 1982-1999 (Box 4)
  - N-P 1981-1999 (Box 5)
    including: Shelly Nameroff, Peter Nijmeijer, Dennis O'Driscoll, D. Okula, Linda Orr, John Peck, Susan Perry, William Phillips, John Piller, Robert Pinsky, Donald Platt, Stan Plumly, Reynolds Price
  - Eric Pankey 1985-2000 (Box 5)
  - Poetry Magazine Publication, Anthologies, Requests, etc. 1980-1999, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Postcards 1975-1999, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Gaetano Prampolini ca. 1983-1996 (Box 5)
  - Pulitzer Prize for Poetry Congratulations 1998 April 8-29, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Pulitzer Prize for Poetry Congratulations 1998 May-Nov (Box 6)
  - R 1981-1999 (Box 6)
    including: John Ridland, Melanie Rehak, John Robbins, Gail Robinson, David Roderick, Bobby Caudle Rogers, Maggie Ross, Paul B. Roth, Mark Rubin, Mark Rudman, Michael Ryan
  - Requests for Recommendations, Evaluations, and Reviews 1982-1999 (Box 6)
  - Sa-Si 1981-1999 (Box 6)
    including: Stephen Sandy, Dennis Schmitz, Bob Schultz, Jim Seay, Charles Seluzicki, Rosa Shand, Robert B. Shaw, Tom Sheehan, Cynthia Shearer, Eugenio De Signoribus, Alex Silberman, Gary Silva
  - Sk-Sz 1968-1999 (Box 6)
    including: David Skeel, Edmund Skellings, Jeffrey Skinner, Anne Slaughter, Arthur Smith, Dave Smith, Jeffery Smith (1961- ), Marcia D. Smith, Ann Snodgrass, Georgia Southworth, Sarah Spence, George Starbuck, George Steele, Lisa Stendig, Camille Jones Strachan, Dabney Stuart, Adrienne Su, Ernest Suarez, David Summers, Larissa Szporluk, Mary Szybist
  - David St. John 1981-1994, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Mary Ann Samyn 1994-2000 (Box 6)
  - Charles Simic 1985-1998, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Maurya Simon 1985-1998 (Box 6)
  - Dean Smith 1992-1999, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Peter Stitt 1981-1999, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Mark Strand 1965-1988, n.d. (Box 7)
  - T-V 1986-19999 (Box 7)
    including: John Tagliabue, Mac Test, Harry Thomas, Alex Thorburn, Richard Tillinghast, James G. Truscott, Chase Twitchell, Jean Valentine, Nance Van Winckel, Patrice Vecchione
  - James Tate 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - Unidentified 1969-2000, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Helen Vendler 1987-1993, n.d. (Box 7)
  - W 1968-1999, n.d. (Box 7)
    including: Sidney Wade, Rosanna Warren, Bruce Weigl, Anne C. Whitehouse, Dara Wier, Corey Wiguil, Richard Wilbur, Ann Williams, John A. Williams, Cynthia Wolfe Wood, Shannon Worrell, C.D. Wright, Jay Wright, Luke Wright, P. Wright, Barbara Wuest, Edith Wylder
  - Y-Z 1967-1999 (Box 7)
    including: Mel Yoken, C. Dale Young, Gary Young, John Yount, Chris Yu, Andrew Zawacki, Mary Zeppa
  - David P. Young 1974 (Box 7)
- INVITATIONS 1980-1999 (Box 7)
- MANUSCRIPTS
  - Appalachia(TMs) [1998] (Box 7)
    Setting Copy, with author's corrections
  - Appalachia Page Proofs, Master Pages, First Pass 1998 Apr 17 (Box 7)
    with author's corrections
  - Appalachia Page Proofs, Master Pages 1998 Jun 4, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Undated Manuscripts n.d. (Box 8)
    Comments on Dante (TMs)
    Comments on a Reading in Early December 1987, Wise County, Virginia (AMs)
    Answers to a Typed List of "Questions for Charles Wright (both AMs & TMs)
    "Words for Pliny from the Burning Volcano"
    "Words for Socrates About Birth & Death"
    "History & the Sea"
    "The Poet's Gaze"
    "Letter from the Stone Age"
    "Star Magic"
    "The Night of 10 August"
    with author's autograph corrections (TMs)
  - "Lost Language" and "On Heaven Considered As What Will Cover Us and Stony Comforter" n.d., (TMs) (Box 8)
    with author's autograph corrections
  - Negative Blue Selected Later Poems Page Proofs 1998 Nov 8, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - "Night Rider" 1999 Dec 2, (TMs & Final Galley Proof) (Box 8)
  - "North Americna Bear" [1999], (TMs) (Box 8)
  - Poetry Notebooks (AMs) containing original hand-written poetry by Wright 1994 Dec-1999 Nov (Box 8)
  - Charles Wright's Translation "Arsenio" and "House by the Sea" by Eugenio Montale Galley Proofs 1999 Jan 26 (Box 8)
  - Charles Wright's Translation "The Dead" by Eutenio Montale Galley Proofs 1999 Jun 22 (Box 8)
  - Writings by Other Authors about Charles Wright and His Work 1998-1999 (Box 8)
    including Brian Clements, Bonnie [Costello], Pat Cunning, Denham's Notes for Senior Seminar for Appalachia and Black Zodiac, J. Stuart Frye, Gill Holland, Henry Hart, J.D. McClatchy, John Mulrooney, and Gaetano Prampolini
- PRINTED & MISCELLANEOUS MATERIAL 1992-1999, n.d. (Box 8)